[music]
There's wind, there's a rough sea.  I don't know
if this video will be heard well, but
confinement.  I trust, I do not confine.
I'm confident that
if you experience any issues with your
audio, I can fix it with Da Vinci Resolve.
Not every day at sea can be as
good as yesterday.  There
must be
windier days every now and then.   It's
also part of the fact that there's
never any dirty air here
because the wind blows it away.
Even if this little dog is a pain in the ass
.
Here is a little,
little dog,
a microscopic dachshund.
It's incredible,
truly incredible, the shape of this
dog.
So, in this video we talk about
something that I think will interest many people.
Let's talk about Quen 3.8
Next Flash.   We
won't talk about the fact that
model names are getting more ridiculous every day
.
Let's pretend nothing happened, let's pretend it
's normal for the model to be called
that,
but we'll talk about a very
interesting technique that this model
uses,
which are the rams, but since we're
speaking in Italian, I should actually
say the gram because in Italian,
English words don't go in the plural,
given that the grammar used is
Italian.
So, I want to come at it from a
slightly oblique point of view
to explain what it's about,
what this new piece of the
model does,
because, you see, there's a lot of
information
that should teach you something, but in
reality you finish watching the video and it
's not that you really understand that extra thing, or reread the article
and it's not that you've really understood that
extra thing.
In my opinion, engrams are part of
these very poorly described technologies.
By the way, I had already talked about this thing
on this channel because
a paper had come out that described
exactly the same technique.  I don't know if it
was actually a paper by Quen, Alibaba,
or maybe a similar group, but I
talked about it in a video.
Now obviously I'm not telling you, I'm linking it
here like YouTubers do, first of all
because I have no idea where the
[ __ ] it is,
but then because I'm telling the same
thing here, better, so why the [ __ ] am I
linking you to the previous video?
But I was saying, I would like that at the end of
this video, those who watch this
video in full, besides making fun
of my hair,
make fun of me,
really understand this technique, what it
does, why it is useful and why it allows you to
have
a model with a certain number of
billions of parameters
that however runs faster than it should
given the quantity of parameters,
despite not being more
technically sparse, because to go
faster I could call a
smaller number of weights per token in the case of a
mix of experts, but this is not the
case.
But I had to say that thing because it is
the basic technique for making
a model go faster with the same weight.
Now, imagine that I have a 310
billion parameter
dense, so for each token I have to
call all of them.  A real mess.
Instead, I only recall a part of it with
the mixer of experts.  But this technique
allows us to go further.
By the way, I'd like to say one thing: this
is a technique that, even if some people don't
agree with me, I think actually
fundamentally concerns your
organization, so it's the first real
step forward
in
organizational techniques.  Then, given how it's done,
someone will say, "Ah, but it's not really
just your organization, there's
gating."  Now let's see in what sense,
but for me it's actually an achievement
of tokenization, it goes
beyond what your current organization is
.  The embeddings
learned during the
course of the course are now very large
because the number of tokens is very large.
But to really understand what
this thing does, let's start by talking about
a hypothetical large language
model that uses a single character
as an input token and a single character
as an output token.
An LM like this, by the way, works
, but it's not just bad.  That is, you can
use instead of the tokens that are
normally used, which are mostly pieces of
words, whole words with spaces,
fragments of words or single
characters as well because your
organizer must allow the LLLM
to also represent inputs and
outputs that are very rare and
therefore cannot be encoded with
aggregate tokens.
Well, instead of doing that, I can instead
disintegrate your organization and
use only the single character, a
bit like Carpati's GPT mini does, which doesn't
use that initial example
from Carpati, because the Large Language
Model
will learn during training that if it sees
PA as input,
and then it will model within its
layers
the fact that that aggregate of
characters corresponds to a specific
concept, which therefore corresponds to a
given embedding,
to a given
representation that has features,
which is a fruit, and so on. But this
[clears throat] means that we
are using a lot of
the Large Language Model's internal capacity to
represent something that could
actually have been learned during
training, and then we say, here's
to actually make room in the weights
within the model for more
interesting things than that thing there, not to
mention the fact that obviously an LM
that uses a single character
as input and output will have problems
with context size, because
with a million tokens you represent
a lot of text with a million
characters, much less.  Then the output
would be one character at a time, so there would be
huge efficiency problems,
but it's also true that you can't go the
other way and therefore [clears throat]
increase
the vocabulary without paying
a lot of explosion problems,
complexity of the output layer and so
on.
So, those who invented
this technique thought, yes, it's
true that we now have tokens that
represent concepts, but
often in reality these concepts come
from multiple tokens together, two or three,
very often.   I'll
give you two examples.  When I say
medieval history,
I am referring to a similar concept that is
made up of three words.
When I say New York, I am referring to
a similar concept that is made up of two
words.  But when I say New York you
visualize the city, you don't visualize
New York and think what York is and then
you think it's new instead of old.
Okay?
Likewise history of the Middle Ages.
That is, I think about the concept of history of
what?  of a particular time range
that immediately come to mind, I do
n't know, monasteries,
eh they come to mind eh eh
Dante, a series
of things associated with the
concept of the Middle Ages come to mind.
Now, just like
a single-
character tokenizer, maybe the model uses a
lot of processing power
to then
aggregate these bytes into
chunks in the model layers.
When I give input to the New York model, I
force it to do the same thing.  There
are a lot of pairs and triplets
of words that force the model to use
a lot of
compute's internal representations during inference
to
transform these n words back into a
single sim concept.
[clears throat]
So, that was the idea.
I take
a huge vocabulary because
Quen's is made up of 51 billion
parameters
and I esh the internal state
of the model of the last two and
last three tokens and then I retrieve an
aggregated version of the last two or three words.
But I don't want this thing here to be
done
in a way that increases the context window.   It
is not another token in the
attention sequence.  Mind you, this is how it
works here.
In short, I want to free the model,
a lot of the model's weights from this
accessory function
that I can largely learn
during training and that then at the
computational level could really
require very little of me
so that I can make room for
higher-level representations and
then use the backbond of the model which
is the tension with the FFN of the block and
so on to do things with it.  more substantial
than bringing New York back.
So this thing happens here.
If the last two tokens of the input
are New York, we make the order of New York,
however with multipliers that
ensure that the order of the two words
is significant.  So ashing
New York is not the same as
ashing York New.  And by ashing, I
mean I'm actually talking about ashing, it's a
fixed mathematical function that is performed on the
input tokens in the first layer.  Okay?
Once I do this ashing,
I actually do 16 ashings, I go and
take
16 little pieces of vectors from a static database which then all
together make up a vector of 2500
of size 2005, something like that.
At this point, in the second layer,
I look at what is the last token that I
processed after the first layer and with
these little pieces that I took this
ashing, mind you, I do it for both
two tokens and three tokens.
Then I have a matrix that tells me how much I
really want to use from this
database of two- and three-
word associations that I have in these 51 billion
parameters.
And how is it done?  Basically this matrix
compares what I took from
this static database
via lashing with the current
internal state of the token, so the token,
the last token processed after it
passed from the attention from the first
integer block of the first layer,
from the second in the second layer, I
then take part
of this information and through this
matrix I leak it
into the internal state of the token already
processed before.  So I'm
enriching,
that is, if it says New York, I'm
taking the token of York and enriching it
with the meaning of New York.  Okay?
If the sequence, the last three, the last
three tokens of the input were
art history, I'm taking the
art token and I'm enriching it with
the meaning of art history.  Okay?
Why is this done on the
second layer?  It's weird, isn't it?  Why the
second layer?
Because this way, during the
processing of the first layer, I have
time, waiting for the latency of the
processing of the first layer, to go and
do this lookup and I don't pay for it.  It will be
masked by the inference time of the
first layer.  Once I go to eh
compute the second layer, I already
got these weights, excuse me, these
little pieces of vector from my database
51 of 51 billion little fragments.
Oh, by the way, why do you make it this
way with 16 little pieces?  Because
then there would be
two all the pairs of words, all the
triplets are a huge number.  So if
I have to compress them into a smaller space
to index these 51. If I
do it with single slices of 2500
components, what happens is that
different concepts end up
overlapping in the same vector.  Instead,
by making 16 different ones I take different
pieces, maybe there will be some that
will collide, but other pieces
won't and so more or less the thing
works.   It's
not that I completely eliminate the
problem of collisions, but I
greatly limit it.
So I was saying, I go and fetch every
time, so art history, art is
enriched by this concept of
art history and by doing the second layer I have
the time, even while I process the first
layer, to do this fetch of this
data.  Then once this token has
been processed at the first layer, I
tell it to this specific matrix that has
this task, but in reality what
I went to take from this from
this layer here, from this
static layer of 51 billion associations,
how much does it really have to do with
art history?  Do we really want
this meaning of
art history to filter through to art?  In this case, yes, but
if the three words were that therefore he did,
maybe not, because that therefore he did is not so
much a concept
that requires a representation in itself.   It
's not New York, it's not art history,
but possibly the model for some
things, however, of the most
interesting representations of however fecel becca for
example these two
could really have it
and then he comes up with something, but he can
decide
from that from this associative table
how much to use,
which is very interesting.
So, what did we conclude?
Number one, these 51 billion
parameters can fit not only in VRAM,
but also in RAM, which is
fast enough for this task.  So if the
model is maybe 130, I don't remember,
I can afford to use that
space in the V for that VAM for
these weights.  plus the 51 billion
accessory parameters
I'm going to put them in RAM which in
many mixed inference systems, for
example the DG Station is in one of these
cases, but also those who have
graphics cards eh in a PC that then has
normal RAM is another of these cases,
eh but even if you have to use the
VRAM anyway, the point is that that is an
associative lookup table.  You're
not computing these 51 billion parameters
in the
matrix multiplications,
you are, that is, they're
essentially free, so the remaining
weights of the model can be
used for other things and the computation
is restricted to just those weights.
So you see how there are several
advantages to using this technique.
Now all this stuff we
talked about, the model takes it
during training,
so basically there's this
very large fixed table learned during
training which is then combined at
runtime based on what is
actually
the context, because the first token
where I'm basically going to
enrich the meaning of
with the lookup I did
is contextualized because it has
paid attention etc. in the
current context and so there's a
very large static part and a small part
that happens at runtime to understand when
I really want to pass
this one of these static situations
into the current state of the large language
model.
Well, I hope we understand each other.  So it
does not increase the grams are
certainly not speculative techoding, but
someone thinks maybe ah Nram I predict
what will happen based on
fixed tables, it has nothing to do with it.  The MTP has
this model, but in other words there is,
I think, a drafter with 4 billion
parameters, if I remember correctly, that performs
this task.
So, it doesn't increase the
context sequence, it's not a part of the
sequence, it doesn't enter the KV Cash, it's an
enrichment of the last token based
on a static table that is taken in
small pieces with a 16-way ashing, eh,
which is then recomposed into a
single vector of 2500 something components
and there is eh it happens at the second second
layer, so that I hide the
latency of going to go and do this
operation here behind the processing of the
first layer.  Furthermore, after the first
layer, the last token has already been
projected by the attention and the Fit
forward network and so on, so I
already have it contextualized and therefore
I can then better decide whether
or not I want to enrich it or how much to
enrich it with this meaning that
I have taken with this static lookup.  And in
this way I took 51 billion
parameters, I took them out of the
computationally intensive part of the
model and made them computationally
very light, then leaving what
remains of the model denser, more
concentrated, difficult to compute, but
at least computes, things that are worth
computing.
I hope I was clear.  See you soon.   What
?